<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The souldiers commission, charge, &amp; revvard both of the deceitfull and negligent, and the faithfull &amp; diligent in the Lords work. Opened in a sermon preached in Christ-Church Dublin, May 14. 1642. Before the state and chief of the Army, upon occasion of the interring of Sir Charles Coote knight, and one of the honourable Privy Council in Ireland. By Faithfull Teate D.D. then lecturer there, now preacher of the gospel in East-Greenwich in Kent.</title>
            <author>Teate, Faithful, b. 1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897696</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2521:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The souldiers commission, charge, &amp; revvard both of the deceitfull and negligent, and the faithfull &amp; diligent in the Lords work. Opened in a sermon preached in Christ-Church Dublin, May 14. 1642. Before the state and chief of the Army, upon occasion of the interring of Sir Charles Coote knight, and one of the honourable Privy Council in Ireland. By Faithfull Teate D.D. then lecturer there, now preacher of the gospel in East-Greenwich in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Teate, Faithful, b. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.H. for T. Underhill, at the Anchor and Bible in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coote, Charles, --  Sir, d. 1642 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137660:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Souldiers Commiſſion, CHARGE, &amp; REVVARD, Both of the DECEITFULL and NEGLIGENT, And the FAITHFULL &amp; DILIGENT in the LORDS Work. Opened in A SERMON Preached in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Dublin, <hi>May</hi> 14. 1642. Before the State and Chief of the ARMY, upon occaſion of the Interring of Sir <hi>CHARLES COOTE</hi> Knight, and one of the Honourable Privy Council in IRELAND.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faithfull Teate</hi> D. D. then Lecturer there, now Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>Eaſt-Greenwich</hi> in KENT.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Cyprian. Epiſt. <hi>2. l. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Homicidium cum admittunt ſinguli crimen eſt, virtus vocatur cum publicè geritur.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 4.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> The time is come, that judgement muſt begin at the houſe of God: and if it firſt begin at us, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the Goſpel of God?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 2.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> If a man ſtrive for maſteries, yet is he not crowned, except he ſtrive lawfully.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>T. Underhill,</hi> at the Anchor and Bible in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:137660:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137660:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir <hi>CHARLES COOTE</hi> Lord Preſident of the Province of <hi>Connaght</hi> in IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall Treatiſe properly belongeth to Your Honour, who are Son and Heir <hi>(tam corporis, quam heroicae virtutis)</hi> to this eminent and Honourable Perſon, whoſe deceaſe gave occaſion to the preaching of this Sermon at as great and ſolemn a Meeting, as I have ſeen in <hi>Ireland.</hi> It was at the firſt intended for the Preſſe, as well as the Pulpit, but till this day hath lain dormant, not in obſervance of the learned<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor.</hi> Arte Poeticâ. Nonum prema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in annum, ſiquid olim ſcripſeris.</note> Poets advice, who counſelleth that a Poem ſhould be kept in under nine years private correction, before it be admitted to publick view; but here was ſomething ſpoken againſt the ceſſation, which was then ſo vigorouſly proſecuted, that it might not be further contradicted, whereof I have written more in another<note n="†" place="margin">In the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my <hi>True Iſraelite.</hi>
               </note> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe formerly publiſhed.</p>
            <p>And indeed had not Your Honour revived it, by giving an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the publication of it now at laſt, it had never appeared in this dreſſe; but being called, it readily obeyed, upon theſe following accounts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the righteouſneſſe and truth of the Lord might be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted
<pb facs="tcp:137660:3"/> to the world, in accompliſhing the predictions here enſuing, both againſt our open enemies, as alſo againſt ſuch as ſecretly oppoſed, and ſubtilly retarded this work of God, which they then pretended to mannage and maintain; who, of all others, have been reputed among wiſe men in all ages, the worſt enemies: For <hi>1.</hi> Their ſin is double, <hi>hypocriſie</hi> being joined unto their <hi>hatred,</hi> and herein they are egregious fools, as <hi>Solomon</hi> termeth them, Prov. <hi>10.18. He that hideth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with lying lips, is a fool. 2.</hi> Of all others they do the moſt miſchief, having more opportunities then enemies without, and being for a time leaſt ſuſpected, as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boet.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> de conſol. Nulla peſtis eſt efficacior ad nocendum, quàm familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s inimicus.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius</hi> rightly obſerveth. <hi>3.</hi> But in the end, God hath threatned to <hi>diſcover</hi> them, Prov. <hi>26.26. Whoſe hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedneſſe ſhall be ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole Congregation;</hi> and then ſhall they be puniſhed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably to their demerits, as <hi>Judas</hi> was, who perfidiouſly betraied his Maſter with a kiſſe. This have many in our daies experimented, and we have ſeen the iſſue: as wave followeth wave, ſo one curſe hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued them after another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the tender mercies and great kindneſſe of our God towards us may be magnified, in fulfilling the deſires of his ſervants, when we called upon him in our diſtreſſe. For though he deprived us of this great, magnanimous and ſucceſsfull Commander, and divers others, upon whom, our eyes (it may be) were too much fixed; to teach us, not to truſt in the arm of fleſh, but in him, who alone doth all: yet hath he anſwered our prayers, in raiſing up continually in times of need, other valiant, vigilant, and victorious Leaders to carry on his own work to a bleſſed period, which ſeemed ſometimes to ceaſe, like the building of the Temple in <hi>Ezra</hi>'s daies.<note place="margin">Ezra 4.13.</note> Time was when theſe Moabites <hi>inſultingly</hi> cried out unto us, <hi>Where is your Engliſh God?</hi> But now may we triumphantly anſwer, You may ſee, if you ſhut not your eyes wilfully againſt the light, that <hi>our God</hi> is in the <hi>heavens,</hi> and hath done whatſoever he pleaſed in the <hi>earth.</hi> Now may we truly ſay, by our own experience, Happy is he that hath the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> for <hi>his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, which made heaven and earth, and keepeth truth for ever, which executeth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the oppreſſed; but the way of the wicked he turneth upſide down.</hi> And now may we demand of you, <hi>Shall not the righteous God avenge his elect, which cry unto him night and day? Surely he will avenge them ſpeedily,</hi> though <hi>he ſeem to forbear long.</hi> What ſay you? we have found it ſo, Can you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137660:3"/>
            <p>Thirdly, That the outgoings of our God in the dawning of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iverances may not be forgotten in the midſt of our daily Trophies for victories ſince acquired; but the whole ſeries of his wonderfull preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of a ſmall remnant of us, may be thankefully recorded <hi>by us,</hi> and <hi>our children after us;</hi> for this doth the Lord expect from us, as may appear by his ſtrait charge given to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he had brought them into the <hi>land of Canaan,</hi> not to forget, how he had wrought for them in the <hi>land of Egypt,</hi> Deut. <hi>6.10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, That hereby (as much as lieth in a paper Monument) the bleſſed memory of this renowned Patriot, after his death, may be <hi>preſerved,</hi> who, under God, was inſtrumental to <hi>preſerve</hi> many lives, by the hazard and loſſe of his own.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 22.1.</hi> Ovid. <hi>l. 2.</hi> Fastorum. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem famam qui bene geſſit, habet.</note> 
               <hi>A good Name</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is rather to be choſen then great riches;</hi> for this followeth a worthy perſon, when riches forſake him. And this is one of the rewards which God hath promiſed to conferre upon his faithfull ſervants, Pſal. <hi>112.6. The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance.</hi> Beſides this, it affordeth laſting comfort to ſurviving friends, and is profitable to others, who thereby are taught to imitate their good examples, whoſe Praiſes are celebrated long after their Funerals are finiſhed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon holy<note n="*" place="margin">De bono vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duitatis. Nobis neceſſaria eſt vita noſtra, aliis fama noſtra.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid, <hi>As a good life is neceſſary for our ſelves, ſo our good name is neceſſary for others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe (Right Honourable) be the reaſons of this late publication of theſe enſuing lines; Now humbly deſiring Your favourable acceptance of my endeavours therein, I commit Your Honour to the <hi>protection</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> of him who is ſtiled <hi>a Man of War,</hi> and <hi>the God of Peace,</hi> in whom, I remain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble ſervant at command, <hi>FAITHFULL TEATE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in</hi> Eaſt-Greenwich.
<date>
                     <hi>1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:137660:4"/>
            <head>TO THE IMPARTIALL READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E pleaſed not to conclude raſhly that this ſubject, <hi>The Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Commiſſion, Charge, and Reward</hi> is therefore like an <hi>Almanack</hi> out of date? becauſe wars in <hi>Ireland</hi> are (bleſſed be God) for the preſent at an end: but well weigh with me theſe following Conſiderations</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe truths are all grounded upon, and extracted from the holy Scriptures, which are always profitable for very good ends and uſes, as the Apoſtle declareth <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They were preached when they were moſt ſeaſonable; although they paſſed not the Preſſe till now, even in the height of war there, when (I ſuppoſe) few or none of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divines had handled this Theame; by reaſon of our long continued Peace formerly in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is wiſdome to keep in ſtore by you a Soveraign Receipt; though there be no preſent need of it, that it may be in readineſſe, when need ſhall require.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As long as we have wars elſe-where by Sea and land, directions are neceſſary for all ſuch as are or ſhall be employed therein, how to demeane themſelves in this work of the Lord aright.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Such as have been actors in theſe precedent wars now paſt, have yet need to look back, and compare all their proceedings from the firſt to the laſt, with the rules which God hath preſcribed them to walk by; that they may have comfort in their weldoings, or repent of their failings.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Although the <hi>Souldiers Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Charge</hi> were terminated; yet the Reward of ſuch as have been faithfull and diligent in this ſervice of the Lord, obſerving his will, and aiming at his glory, ſhall never have end. To God alone through Jeſus Chriſt be all Glory world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137660:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON preached at the Funeral of Sir CHARLES COOTE <hi>ſenior,</hi> who Deceaſed the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREM. 48.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully, and curſed be he that keepeth back his ſword from blood.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter is compriſed <hi>Moabs</hi> doom, which is the deſtruction of that Nation, <hi>v.</hi> 8. the ſpoiler ſhall come upon every City (ſaith the Lord) <hi>no City ſhall eſcape,</hi> but <hi>they ſhall all</hi> be deſolate, without any inhabitant; <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. for this end the Prophet enumerateth the ſins wherewith the righteous Lord was incenſed to paſs this ſentence upon them, and theſe were carnal confidence, in their riches, <hi>v.</hi> 7. and in their numbers, might and ſtrength for war, <hi>v.</hi> 14. their idolatry, <hi>v.</hi> 13. contempt of God, <hi>v.</hi> 26. and deriſion of his people, <hi>v.</hi> 27. arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, pride and haughtineſs of heart, <hi>v.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>This verſe containeth the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> charge, who were to be the executioners of that judgement on the <hi>Moabites,</hi> to do their work throughly, without ſparing one or other; <hi>Curſed be he</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully,</hi> or <hi>negligently,</hi> as it is in the margin; for the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth both: And that all may know what is here meant by the work of the Lord, he expoundeth himſelf in the next words, <hi>Curſed is he that keepeth back his ſword from blood;</hi> that is, from the ſlaughter of the <hi>Moabites.</hi> Hence we clearly gather,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the right waging of a lawfull war, is a work that God will own.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This truth is further ratified by thoſe titles wherewith the Lord ſtileth himſelf elſwhere, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.16. <hi>The Lord of hoſts is his name;</hi> and <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. the Lord is called <hi>a Man of war;</hi> as alſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137660:5"/> the battels that <hi>David</hi> fought, are termed <hi>the Lords battels,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.17. and he is ſaid to go forth againſt the Churches enemies in the Name of the Lord of hoſts, <hi>the God of the Armies of Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. This might ſuffice for proof, but becauſe this truth hath been of old, and is at this day by ſome much controverted, I ſhall briefly annex ſome other grounds for it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Ameſ. <hi>de conſcion.</hi> l. 5. c. 33. ſect. 4.</note>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. God cannot but allow of that which is done <hi>by vertue of his own command,</hi> provided alwaies that it be performed in a right manner. Now God hath commanded, that <hi>whoſo ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed; for in the Image of God made he man,</hi> Gen. 9.6. Thus he commanded <hi>Gideon</hi> to go againſt the <hi>Midianites</hi> to ſmite them, and promiſed to go with him, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.14, 16. ſaying to him, <hi>Go in this thy might, and ſave Iſrael from them, have not I ſent thee?</hi> and again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.18. <hi>With good advice</hi> (ſaith the Lord by the mouth of <hi>Solomon) make war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As he giveth a Commiſſion, ſo he giveth his <hi>Spirit</hi> to ſome <hi>for ſtrength to turn the battel from the gate,</hi> Iſa. 28.6. as well as for judgement to him that ſitteth in judgement; where he ſheweth that a ſouldier is as neceſſary in time of war, as a Judge in time of peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He furniſheth thoſe whom he calleth forth for his ſervice, not only with ſtrength, but likewiſe with <hi>ſingular dexterity and skill:</hi> he teacheth their <hi>hands to war, and their fingers to fight,</hi> as he did <hi>Davids,</hi> for which he bleſſeth the Lord, who fitted him for the work, and then employed and bleſſed him in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.1.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We finde him <hi>highly commending</hi> thoſe who have behaved themſelves excellently in this His work, in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.11—26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where we have a catalogue of <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies reckoned up, according to their ſeveral ranks and degrees of proweſs, and they are called more Honourable then others, who were more valiant, and ſlew more then others, <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21, 23.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We finde him alſo <hi>diſtributing</hi> large and ample <hi>rewards</hi> to men eminently ſerviceable in this kind; for <hi>he made David a ſure houſe,</hi> becauſe he fought the battels of the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.28. Loe here, <hi>Davids</hi> houſe was ſurely founded in the blood of the enemies of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>He diſpoſeth</hi> (as he pleaſeth) <hi>of the events of warre,</hi> and the Saints have ever aſcribed their victories unto him alone, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11. and have accounted them exceeding great mercies, and bleſſed him for the ſame, which they would not have done, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137660:5"/> would rather have confeſſed themſelves to have been guilty of hainous ſins, as of cruelty and murther in obtaining them, if ſo be warfar in it ſelf had been unlawfull. <hi>Our fathers</hi> (ſaith the Church) <hi>got not the land in poſſeſſion by their own ſword, neither did their own arm ſave them, but</hi> thy right hand <hi>(O Lord) and thine arm, and the light of thy countenance, becauſe thou hadſt a favour to them. Through thee will we puſh down our enemies; through thy Name will we tread them under that riſe up againſt us,</hi> Pſal. 44.3, &amp; 5.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, The Lord hath <hi>ſharply taxed</hi> ſuch as have been called to this work, and have refuſed to come, either through diviſions, or imployments of their own, either about husbandry or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, as you may ſee in <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.14, 16, 17. where we have thoſe tribes recorded to their everlaſting honour, that came rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to <hi>Barak</hi> againſt <hi>Amalek;</hi> as <hi>Ephraim, Zebulun,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> and <hi>Naphtali:</hi> and on the other ſide, thoſe are for ever branded with ignominy that withdrew themſelves. <hi>For the diviſions of Reuben</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were great thoughts of heart,</hi> who abode among the <hi>ſheepfolds. Gilead abode beyond Jordan,</hi> and <hi>Dan remained in ſhips. Aſher continued on the ſea ſhore,</hi> in his crooks, when they ſhould have been all as one man in the Army, in the field againſt the enemy. And here in my Text he curſeth them bitterly who came to the work, but performed it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Septuagint render it, <hi>negligently,</hi> or <hi>careleſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe ſeven grounds others might be added, but it may ſufficiently appear by theſe, that it is not only lawfull ſometimes to go to war; but very ſinfull in ſome caſes not to do it, and they that do it, may bring a curſe upon themſelves, not for doing it, but for doing it remiſly, and not with their beſt skill and utmoſt vigor.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Is it ſo then, that God oft gives Commiſſion to men, and ſends them to the wars, and promiſeth to go with them; and for that end he furniſheth them with ſtrength and skill, and condemneth thoſe that refuſe to go; or that going, do his work deceitfully: but highly commendeth all ſuch as behave themſelves diligently and valiantly, and rewards them with victory, renown, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other bleſſings? <hi>This ſerves,</hi> in the firſt place, <hi>to confute all thoſe that hold all war under the Goſpel utterly unlawfull:</hi> and thus of old did the <hi>Photinians,</hi> whoſe opinion is alſo revived by ſome in our daies. I ſhall inſtance only in one of our ſouldiers, who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137660:6"/> in his ſickneſſe was much troubled for killing (as he ſaid) one of the Rebels in battel, all his ſins were not ſo grievous to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as that fact (as he complained to the by-ſtanders) his reaſon was, becauſe Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter, Put up thy ſword into the ſheath; he that taketh the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> But you will ſay, perhaps this might be ſome temptation, whereby Satan endeavoured to perplex a dying man: I ſhall therefore ſhew you,<note n="*" place="margin">Vide <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard.</hi> loc. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie.</note> how that the judgements of ſundry ancient and learned Fathers have been leavened with this error, who have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to hold it forth to others as an orthodox truth. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> demandeth thus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> de coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ militis.</note> 
               <hi>Licebit in gladio verſari,</hi> &amp;c. Can it be lawfull to uſe the ſword, ſince the Lord pronounceth that he ſhall periſh by the ſword, that taketh it? <hi>anne praelio operabitur filius pacis, cui nec litigare conveniet?</hi> How can he fight, who is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to contend?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">l. 6. <hi>Divin. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</hi> c. 20.</note>In like manner <hi>Lactantius</hi> affirmeth, that in the ſixt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> there ought to be no exception made, <hi>Quin occidere hominem ſit ſemper nefas;</hi> but that it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull in any caſe whatſoever to kill a man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l. 2.</hi> contra Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, Hom. <hi>15.</hi> in Joſ.</note>I ſhall adde to theſe <hi>Origen,</hi> who pleadeth that Chriſt hath taken away all warres in the new Teſtament, and he ſuppoſeth that the Apoſtles would never have delivered the books of the Jewiſh Hiſtories to the Diſciples of Chriſt, who came to bring peace, to be read in Churches, <hi>Niſi bella iſta carnalia figuram ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualium bellorum gererent,</hi> unleſſe thoſe carnal wars bore the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of ſpiritual wars.</p>
            <p>All which well conſidered, it is very requiſite that all men, eſpecially ſouldiers, ſhould be well informed in this point: for without knowledge the heart is not good; and without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God; to the unbeleeving all things are unclean, even their mindes and conſciences are defiled. And for your eſtabliſhing in this truth, firſt weigh well the former grounds, and then you ſhall confeſſe that 'tis a work very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, to fight againſt the enemies of Gods Church, and by how much the more difficult and dangerous it is, by ſo much the more meritorious is it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2. 2 <hi>ae</hi> q. 40. <hi>artic.</hi> 2.</note> not in reſpect of God (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> holdeth) but in reſpect of them for whoſe ſake it is undertaken. How do <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> extoll <hi>Zebulun</hi> and <hi>Naphtali</hi> in their ſong, for jeoparding their lives unto death <hi>in the high places of the field?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:137660:6"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> And in the next place, mark well the invalidity of ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections as are raiſed againſt this doctrine: The firſt is in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.39. <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Reſiſt not evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is forbidden ſelf-revenge, but not juſt ſelf-defence, which the very law of nature teacheth every living creature; as the heathen Orator ſhews, <hi>Ut ſe, vitam, corpuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tueatur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic.</hi> 1. l. <hi>offic.</hi>
               </note> and Chriſt in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.39. proclaims to all Chriſtians, what he would have them to do in caſe of unjuſt aſſault, with a <hi>Noverint univerſi; This know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that if the good man of the houſe had known in what watch the thief would come, he would have watched, and would not have ſuffered his houſe to be broken up.</hi> Yet I have known ſome, whoſe conſciences for the want of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſts minde herein, have ſuffered thieves to break into their houſes once and again, to wound themſelves, and to take away their goods, without reſiſtance, when they might have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them, if they hid pleaſed; who alledged for their ſo doing that prohibition, <hi>Reſiſt not evil.</hi> But how forcible the law of nature is, the Apoſtle declareth, whe e he argueth from it againſt a mans wearing long hair, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> in locum. à natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ deciderunt, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Doth not even nature it ſelf teach you, that if a man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But Chriſt goes on in the foreſaid place, ſaying, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall ſmite thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other alſo.</hi> How then can it be lawfull to go to war?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe words are not to be taken ſimply, as <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate perverted them in a ſcornfull manner, but comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as if our Lord had ſaid, When an injury is offered, be ye ſo far from perſonal revenge, that ye be rather ready to take as much more wrong in word or deed, than to recompence evil for evil. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> being commanded to be ſmitten on the mouth by <hi>Ananias</hi> the High-prieſt,<note place="margin">Act. 23.2, 3.</note> was ſo far from turning his cheek to the ſmiter, that he called <hi>Ananias</hi> a whited wall, and told him, that God ſhould ſmite him for his injuſtice: Neither did he ſing a <hi>palinodia,</hi> as if he had offended in ſo ſaying (as ſome would have it) when he replied to thoſe that ſtood by, and demanded of him by way of objurgation, <hi>Revileſt thou Gods High-prieſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> I wiſt not that he is the High-prieſt, for ſo it is in the Greek,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph.</hi> l. 20. c. 6, &amp; 7.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, meaning thereby, as <hi>Beza</hi> proves out of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> that he was no lawfull High-prieſt, but an Uſurper.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. But the New Teſtament is ſo far from allowing of war as the Old Teſtament doth, that Chriſt flatly forbids it, <hi>Matth.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:137660:7"/> 26.52. where he bids <hi>Peter, Put up thy ſword,</hi> and renders this reaſon, <hi>for all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though in this caſe our Saviour forbids <hi>Peter</hi> to make uſe of the ſword, and in him all others, without a due calling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; yet<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> contra Fauſt. Nulla ergo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtantia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientis, ſed ratione diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantis tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diverſitate praecepta, vet conſitia vel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m ſſa mutantur.</note> elſewhere this Prince of peace doth allow his Apoſtles, and in them all others upon juſt occaſions to buy, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to uſe the ſword; as you may reade in the Goſpel of <hi>Luke</hi> 22.36. <hi>He that hath no ſword, let him</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſell his garment, and buy one:</hi> Which cannot be underſtood of any ſpiritual ſword, as ſome would fain pretend, being otherwiſe unable to evade this clear Text: For what ſpiritual ſword can the price of a mans garment purchaſe? and what got <hi>Simon Magus</hi> but a curſe, for offering the Apoſtles money for the gift of conferring the holy Ghoſt? in <hi>Acts</hi> 8.19, 20. when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Goſpel proof we have in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. where the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is ſaid not to <hi>bear the ſword in vain,</hi> and therefore evil doers ſhould be afraid; for <hi>he is the miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon malefactors:</hi> and for that end, if they become numerous,<note n="*" place="margin">Ameſ. l. 5. <hi>De conſci.</hi> c. 33. Sect. 9.</note> he may and ought to levy and proſecute war againſt them, till they be ſubdued.</p>
            <p>Take a third, that ſo by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, this truth may be ſo confirmed, that none that have underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may ſcruple at it any more. In <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7, 8. we have <hi>war in heaven,</hi> that is, the Church, <hi>Michael and his Angels, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> with his ſouldiers, fighting and prevailing againſt the Dragon, in the perſecuting Emperors, <hi>Maxentius, Maximinus,</hi> and <hi>Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> his inſtruments. Again, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.14. we finde the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>making war</hi> with, and overcoming the Beaſt; and the Saints on the Lambs ſide, are ſaid to be <hi>called, and choſen, and faithfull.</hi> 3. Laſtly, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12, 14. the Lord Chriſt, there termed, <hi>the Word of God,</hi> is brought in upon a white horſe, having his veſture dipt in blood, to ſhew the exceeding great ſlaughter of his foes, both paſt and future, with his Armies following him, who are ſaid to be <hi>in heaven,</hi> becauſe the people of God have their converſation there; and theſe joyn in battel with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, <hi>and the Kings of the earth and their Armies,</hi> and vanquiſh them. Now what better ſervice can the devil poſſibly deviſe to do his eldeſt ſon Antichriſt, <hi>aliàs</hi> the Pope, then to perſwade
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137660:7"/> Chriſtians that they ought not to fight, or at leaſt not for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; ſince he full well knows that theſe are they that muſt give him his mortall blow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Souldiers being thus informed of the lawfulneſſe of a juſt war, muſt learn in the next place, that Gods work muſt be performed in a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dionyſ. Carthuſ. q. d.</hi> Maledicetur exercitus Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum, ſi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitionem Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitarum juxta Dei voluntatem non adimpleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nec tamen id faciendo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicti fuerunt, quia non recta id intentione e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerunt, ſed ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo cupido at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> crud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li.</note> right manner; or elſe ſuppoſe the work be Gods, yet the party ſhall be accurſed that doth it <hi>negligently</hi> or <hi>deceitfully,</hi> as my Text affirms. Would you then be partakers of the benefit of <hi>Solomons</hi> prayer, in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.34, 35. it is not enough to be of the number of Gods people, nor to go out to war againſt Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but you muſt alſo <hi>go by the way which God ſhall ſend you,</hi> and then you may be certain that he will hear from the heavens your prayer, and maintain your cauſe. Would you be crowned? then muſt you <hi>ſtrive lawfully,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.5. <hi>Aquinas</hi> extracteth out of divers parts of <hi>Auguſtines</hi> works, ſome Rules for direction in this way: But I ſhall acquaint you with what the great General of all Armies requireth of you, as you may readily find with me, if you conſult with his holy Word.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>1</label> 1. He that goeth to war, <hi>muſt be ſure that the cauſe which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh, is juſt:</hi> For 1. Otherwiſe it cannot be the Lords work, who is <hi>a God that takes no pleaſure in wickedneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 5.4. 2. How can they that take an evil cauſe in hand, pray to God with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for good ſucceſſe, or expect a bleſſing upon their enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, ſince they fight againſt God? <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. 3. He that knows he is upon good ground, fights manfully, and embraceth even death undauntedly; whereas on the other ſide, conſciouſneſſe of an evil cauſe, emaſculates the ſpirits, and rendreth death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly dreadfull. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.1. <hi>The wicked flee when none purſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Propert.</hi> l. 4. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>but the righteous are bold as a lion. Frangit &amp; attollit vires in mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cauſa.</hi> 4. If the parties, who either raiſe or endeavour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an unjuſt war, be therein ſlain, their blood ſhall be on their own heads; or if they kill others, they become murderers in the ſight of God: Yea, let all Incendiaries, Ringleaders,<note place="margin">☜</note> and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters of unlawfull wars know that they are<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>J Lipſius.</hi> Multae bodiè ſunt bellorum faces utinam vel aquis Stygiis resting uendae. de Militia Rom. <hi>l. 2. dial. 7.</hi>
               </note> guilty of all the ſlaughters, rapes, rapines, burnings, and outrages, which be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>ab ovo ad malum,</hi> in ſuch combuſtions, and one day ſhall anſwer for them; and yet more, if ye will believe the Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, upon ſuch ſhall come all the righteous blood ſhed upon the earth, from the blood of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> unto the laſt believers blood, whoſe death was procured or occaſioned by them, <hi>Mat.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:137660:8"/> 23.34, 35. For which cauſe it is truly affirmed, that in ſpiritual <hi>Babylon will be found the blood of Prophets, and of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth for righteouſneſſe ſake,</hi> Revel. 18.24. becauſe modern perſecutors juſtifie all that their forefathers,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.31.</note> (as our Saviour calleth precedent murtherers of Saints and Prophets) have done, by the like facts.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>2</label> 2. A ſouldier being a miniſter imployed by authority for the execution of juſtice upon malefactors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug</hi> in <hi>Pſa. 50.</hi> Ille Justus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor qui non habet quod in ipſo puniatur.</note> that cannot otherwiſe be reſtrained, <hi>ought to repent of his own ſins, before he be fit to puniſh others for their offences.</hi> For want of this the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though their cauſe were juſt, fell twice before the <hi>Benjamites, Judg.</hi> 20.21. For, <hi>he that judgeth another, and doth the ſame things, condemneth himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theophyl.</hi> Videtur hic ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem dirigere ad magiſtratus praecipue Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, ut qui or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi terrarum praeſiderent. Magiſtratuum enim est judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall no waies eſcape the judgement of God, Rom.</hi> 2.1, 3. On which place <hi>Theophylact</hi> conceiveth that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle chiefly intends Magiſtrates: For if it be a reproveable thing in Miniſters of the Word, to reprove their hearers for ſuch faults as themſelves are guilty of, before they themſelves have repented of them; much more hainous is it in the Miniſters of Juſtice to execute puniſhments upon delinquents, while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main guilty of the ſame, or ſuch like crimes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>3</label> 3. Before men go forth to war, <hi>Let God be ſought to, by publick faſting and prayer:</hi> So began <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.3. when multitudes of <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and others came againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> who had no might againſt them, neither knew they what to do, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and received a gracious anſwer and aid from above. <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> ſaid God, <hi>nor diſmaied, neither ſhall ye need to fight: q. d.</hi> You have done enough already, in ingaging me in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, now only <hi>ſtand ye ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> v. 17. Behold here the wonderfull efficacy of faſting and prayer, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we in this City have had very happy and remarkable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I ſhall relate but one memorable paſſage for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of this to all impartial hearers: After the breaking out of this horrid Rebellion, which began <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. 1641. preſently the State had information that the enemies deſign was to beſiege <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and therefore they ſent all the forces which then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly could be raiſed, to the fortification of that Garriſon; after whoſe departure we had no conſiderable ſtrength left behind for defence of this City, and ſome of thoſe we had were perſons lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to be confided in. The numerous and ſubtil enemies percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this, drew together and begirt us round. In this forlorn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137660:8"/> ſome Preachers preſſed the Council daily for a publique faſt, as the only remedy left; but it could not be obtained (through the averſneſſe of ſome who ſhould have been moſt forward in ſuch a work) till the 12 of <hi>November</hi> enſuing; and now mark, on that very evening after our general humiliation, the Lord gave a gracious return, and taught us that our beſt weapons were (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks) prayers and tears. For as the Spirit of God came upon <hi>Othn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el,</hi> and raiſed him up to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their diſtreſs, <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.9, 10. <hi>when they cried unto him;</hi> ſo did the ſpirit of mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and ſtrength fall ſuddenly upon this deceaſed Senator, and ancient expert ſouldier, who had been long before this day, by age and ſickneſſe, almoſt decrepit, hardly able to ſet his foot to the ground, who comes to the Council Table, and tendereth his ſervice to go forth againſt the enemy, accounting it (he ſaid) more eligible to die in the field, than to be ſlain within doors. This motion was no leſſe acceptable then ſeaſonable; but ſome thought it would prove abortive, ſaying, The good mans ſpirit is willing, but his body is weak: Others demanded where he would have men for the ſervice? but our preſſing exigencies would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no long conſultations; the State knew his priſtine valour, commended his preſent reſolution, and promiſed him their beſt aſſiſtance. He goes forth, and with all ſpeed taketh up ſuch men as firſt came to hand, moſtly ſuch as had been ſtripped, and were half ſtarved, and had never been trained; theſe he led forth, to the number of ſeven hundred (at moſt) into the County of <hi>Wicklow,</hi> where the ſtrength of the enemy was concentred; he fals on, at the firſt our men were diſranked, he skilfully rallies them on a ſudden, and in fine, routeth the enemy, and returneth without the loſſe of any one man, excepting one only, whom he ſhot himſelf as he was running away to the Rebels. This mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſeemed to us no leſſe than a Reſurrection from the dead: What matter of joyfull thankfulneſſe did it afford us? How were we animated to continue our weekly daies of humiliation, with exceeding great concourſe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> into our Congregations; and as <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> prevailed againſt <hi>Amalek,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> while <hi>Moſes</hi> held up his hand, and when he let down his hand <hi>Amalek</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed; ſo as long as we here continued in publique prayer and ſupplication, our party prevailed in the field, till they became maſters of the field during the ſpace of a whole year and half. But now, mark again, I pray, ſome of the City Miniſters being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137660:9"/> ſore preſſed with this ſo long continued burden of keeping two weekly Sabbaths, as they ſaid, made their addreſſes to the Lords of the Council for mitigation, alledging that our enemies were well brought under, our ſtraits and fears removed, and we become their ſuperiors, and therefore that a monethly faſt might well ſuffice. And at length their daily importunity prevailed, and we were inforced to draw up our nets, before the fiſh was caught. Now no ſooner had we intermitted one faſt day, but diſmall news was brought from our Army the very next day, that Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> Gods viſible inſtrument of our preſervation from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe direfull wars, was ſhot at <hi>Trim,</hi> in his purſuit of the enemy, by treachery (as ſome ſtrongly conceive) but that I leave to the plenary deciſion of the laſt day. And now may any eaſily preſage which way we are going, even back into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe again. Oh! what an incomparable loſſe have we all ſuſtained in the fall of this great man? I cannot expreſſe it, but a ſhort time ſhall diſcover it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.5.</note> 
               <hi>How terrible, O God, are thy doings toward the children of men?</hi> Return, O Lord, for thy ſervants ſake, that a ſmall remnant of thy people in this Land of ire become not like <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> for the Lords ſake. Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Peers, worthy Commanders, and all dear Chriſtians, would you have the Lord not to depart from us, but to go forth with our Hoſts? you muſt continue wreſtling with him, with prayers and tears,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.28.</note> and then if you prevail <hi>Jacob</hi>-like with God, you ſhall alſo prevail with men.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>4</label> 4. <hi>Adde to prayer, faith.</hi> We muſt all live by faith, and pray in faith; but above all it is primely neceſſary in a Chriſtian ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; for he is not only to fight againſt fleſh and blood, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>principalities and powers,</hi> Eph. 6.12. and ſuppoſe you van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the former, and be ſubdued by the latter through unbelief, it will not be ſo much as a <hi>ſemi</hi> victory. But if you build upon the Rock Chriſt by faith, the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt you, much leſſe ſhall the ſerpents ſeed, wicked men overcome you. How victorious a grace faith is, even in wars with men, may be ſeen in <hi>Gedeon,</hi> and <hi>Barak, Jephtha, David,</hi> and others, <hi>who through faith ſubdued Kingdoms, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, out of weakneſſe were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliens,</hi> Heb. 11.33, 34. Wherefore did the Lord deliver the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> and the <hi>Lubims</hi> a huge hoſt, with very many Chariots and Horſemen into the hands of <hi>Aſa?</hi> not for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137660:9"/> his multitudes, or skill or power; but becauſe he relied upon the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.8. Therefore although others truſt in their owne preparations, numbers, policy, ſtrength, skill, or former ſucceſſe; let your onely confidence be placed in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, power, and preſence of God, as <hi>Davids</hi> was, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>5</label> 5. Heathens require proweſſe and valour in martial men, and certainly <hi>God cannot abide cowardlineſſe in ſuch as fight his battels;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic</hi> pro <hi>Mar.</hi> Certè in armis, militum virtus multum juvat.</note> for ſaith he to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 20.1. <hi>When thou goeſt out to battel againſt thine enemies, and ſeeſt horſes and chariots, and a people more than thou, be not afraid of them.</hi> And when they approach to battel, he commandeth the Officers to ſpeak to the people, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>What man is fearful and faint-hearted? let him goe and return unto his houſe, leſt his brethrens heart faint as well as his heart,</hi> v. 8. But what heathen Authors can afford you ſuch encouragements and valid incentives to true valour, as the word of God doth? <hi>Be ſtrong, and of a good Courage,</hi> ſaith the Lord to <hi>Joſhua, have not I commanded thee?</hi> Ch. 1.9. Again, <hi>Be not afraid nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for the Lord thy God is with thee, whitherſoever thou goeſt.</hi> The firſt argument here is taken from Gods Commandement, and that doth not only require, but alſo infuſe courage into the hearts of all obedient hearers. 2. Mark his promiſe, <hi>I will be with thee whitherſoever thou goeſt,</hi> this if it be rightly laid hold on, will ſo fortifie the Spirit, that if ten thouſand ſhould hemme you in, you could not be afraid: it will alſo defend you, and repel your ſtouteſt foes, even then when they are moſt confident, and all outward helps ſeem to fail you. Adde to theſe a third, which <hi>Joab</hi> uſeth to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> 2 Sam. 10.12. <hi>Be of good courage, let us play the men for our people, and for the cities of our God: and let the Lord doe that which ſeemeth good in his eyes.</hi> Loe, here a triple coard never to be broken, let us put them together. God ſets you a work, God will be with you in the work, and for God and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern Epiſt. 129</hi> Eccleſiae inimicos expug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare decet.</note> his Church you fight: Who would deſire to die better, than in ſuch ſervice as this?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>6</label> 6. <hi>Obedience to ſuperiours</hi> may well challenge the next place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe Directions. Mat. 8.9. <hi>I am a man,</hi> ſaith the Centurion, <hi>under authority, having Souldiers under me: and I ſay to this man goe, and he goeth: and to another come, and he cometh.</hi> The want of this drove <hi>David</hi> to greater ſtraits than all his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries could do, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:137660:10"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>7</label> 7. What a glorious ornament would it be to Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; <hi>if Juſtice both Commutative and Diſtributive</hi> might be found in Camps? when as it hath been of old, and ſtill is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of ſuch places, that there luſt ruleth in ſtead of law, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſque locum ſibi vendicat enſis.</hi> 1. Juſtice requires that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran. Seſſ. 6.</hi> Bellum cum hostibus &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ramus: cum noſtris be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiis certe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperandis quae noſtra ſunt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendamus.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent perſons, eſpecially ſuch as for whoſe help ſouldiers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come, ſhould be defended, and not wronged by them. See <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> charge, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.14. when the ſouldiers demanded of him, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi> he anſwered, <hi>Do violence to no man, neither accuſe any falſly, and be content with your wages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Juſtice commandeth that notorious offenders in no caſe be ſpared; <hi>Agag</hi> was worthy of death, <hi>Saul</hi> ſaved his life, and loſt his Kingdome for this indulgence. Fooliſh pitty to<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch.</hi> Lenitas erga ſceleratos eſt in bonos crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor is cruelty to your ſelves, and many others. <hi>Ahab</hi> let <hi>Benhadad</hi> eſcape, hereat the Lord was diſpleaſed, and ſent him a tart meſſage by the Prophet, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt let go out of thy hand, a man whom I appointed to deſtruction, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſaith the Lord) ſhall thy life go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There ought to be a diſtributive Juſtice among your ſelves. I beſeech you be not offended with me, for ſhewing you the way of God to your own temporal and eternal proſperity; and though carnal reaſon will perhaps ſuggeſt other counſel to you, yet <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you him in all your ways,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſhall direct your paths.</hi> The ſpoils taken from the enemy ſhould not be ingroſſed by ſome; but by an equall diſtribution imparted to all: See <hi>Davids</hi> order in this caſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.22, 24. Some of his men were faint, and ſo were caſt behind, when the reſt followed him to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, wherefore after they returned back with great ſpoiles, ſome of them would not allow any ſhare of the prey taken, unto their fellows ſo caſt behind, for which cauſe they are termed <hi>wicked men and men of Belial,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> told them, they ſhould not do ſo, but they ſhould all ſhare alike, even they that tarried by the ſtuffe, as well as they that went down to the battel: and he made it (ſaith the text) <hi>a ſtatute and an ordinance for Iſrael unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>8</label> 8. <hi>The ends for which war is undertaken and maintained ought ever to be regarded,</hi> and theſe ought to be Gods glory, the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good men, the puniſhment of hainous offenders, and the ſetling of peace in the Common-wealth: not covetuouſneſſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137660:10"/> deſire of revenge, or affectation of dominion, or vain-glory; for which <hi>Jehoaſh</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thus reproved <hi>Amaziah, Thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſmitten</hi> Edom, <hi>and thine heart hath lifted thee up: glory of this, and tarry at home, for why ſhouldeſt thou meddle to thy hurt, that thou ſhouldeſt fall, and</hi> Judah <hi>with thee,</hi> 2 King. 14.10. But <hi>Amazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> refuſed to hear, and therefore he and <hi>Judah</hi> were worſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iſrael,</hi> v. 11. The end of wars is peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Dei <hi>l 19 c. 12.</hi> Pacem conſtat belli eſſe finem optabilem.</note> ſaith <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>in Serm. de verbis Domini, Apud veros Dei cultores ipſa bella pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata ſunt, quae non cupiditate, aut crudelitate, ſed pacis ſtudio ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur, ut mali coerceantur, &amp; boni ſubleventur.</hi> Among the true worſhippers of God their very wars are peaceable, being waged not for luſt or cruelty, but with deſire of peace, that bad men may be ſuppreſſed, and good men aided. Theſe be the chief di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, to which more might be added, but I proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Are wars thus waged, the work of the Lord? here is matter of <hi>terror to the enemies of Gods Church; and comfort to ſuch as go forth againſt them in this way of God;</hi> for although the former may ſeem for a time to prevail, yet in due time they ſhall be ſubdu'd, and God will be ſure to ariſe at laſt, to maintain his own cauſe. This is aſſigned the reaſon why the <hi>Hagarites</hi> and many others fell down ſlain before two tribes and an half, <hi>becauſe the war was of God,</hi> 1 Chon. 5.18,—22. Let us not then be troubled with the multitude of the Rebels, nor their bloody threats and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions if they prevail; nor yet with the ſucceſſe now and then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending their enterprizes: but let us weigh their cauſe with our own in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and then all may ſee whom God in fine will ſide with, when he hath truly humbled and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his people for deliverance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The juſt Cauſes of war</hi> in Scripture are ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Men may lawfully defend themſelves and friends being <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly aſſaulted,</hi> having a Calling from God ſo to do. Thus <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> fought for his Nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> and reſcued him and his Allies, having ſlain the invaders, and is highly commended for it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.14, 18, 19. and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 22.2.</hi> Multò magis licitum eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vitam, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domum <hi>Aquin. 22. q. 64.</hi>
               </note> he that defendeth not himſelf, when he may, is guilty of his own wrongs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> took up Arms againſt the Children of <hi>Reuben,</hi> the <hi>Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe they would have therewith purſued them; if they had not given them good ſatisfaction, for <hi>innovation in Religion</hi> and Gods Worſhip, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.11, 12.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:137660:11"/>3. God approves of the puniſhing of <hi>Capital offenders,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as protect them by force of Armes,</hi> Judg. 20.13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> purſued the <hi>Amalekites</hi> by the Lords appointment, and ſmote them for<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran. Seſſ. 4.</hi> Publicas inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias, uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones injuſtas, princeps aequo animo ferre no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debet: ſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis viribus, quae ſua ſunt ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, arrepta ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis recipere.</note> 
               <hi>plundring Ziglag,</hi> and ſo recovered the goods and perſons whom in a hoſtile manner they had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.8, 16.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God proclaimed an irreconcileable war between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Amalek</hi> till they ſhould blot out the remembrance of <hi>Amalek</hi> from under heaven. Here is an extirpation of Nation and name commanded; if you demand for what fault? The Lord giveth in their Inditement, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.17, 18. <hi>Remember what Amalek did to thee by the way,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Iſrael, how he met thee coming from Egypt, and ſmote the hindmoſt of thee, even all that were feeble behind thee, when thou waſt faint and weary; and he feared not God. Thou ſhalt never forget it,</hi> v. 19.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wherefore did <hi>David</hi> deſtroy the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> and beſiege <hi>Rabbah?</hi> but for the <hi>Villany of Hanun</hi> in taking <hi>Davids</hi> ſervants, and ſhaving off one half of their beards, and cutting off their garments in the middle, even to their Buttocks, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them away in this guiſe? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.4. and 11.1. Did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> let the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of either ſex eſcape ſo?</p>
            <p n="7">7. King <hi>Ahab</hi> ſlew <hi>Naboth for his Vineyard, and after his death tooke poſſeſſion:</hi> for which reaſon the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> told him from the Lord that in the place where dogs licked <hi>Naboths</hi> blood, the dogs ſhould alſo lick his blood, even the Kings, for murthering his honeſt Subject, which accordingly came to paſſe; for after he was ſlain in battel, he was brought to <hi>Samaria,</hi> where one waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his chariot in the pool, and the dogs licked his blood, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of the Lord, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.19.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe grounds, and other apparent cauſes have we of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation to proceed in like ſort againſt our Antichriſtian and bloody adverſaries in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who 1. Have been long man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated to groſſe Idolatry. 2. Againſt the Law of the Land they took the ſword. 3. Committed at the firſt unheard of and prodigious maſſacres of men women and children without reſpect, even of one hundred and fifty thouſand Chriſtians (according to their own reckoning) living inoffenſively and ſecurely among them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Having firſt entred into a Covenant written with their own blood to extirpate all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with their memorial: herein
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137660:11"/> imitating that notorious conſpirator of old, curſed <hi>Cataline,</hi> who firſt bound all his fellow-traytors with a curſe, and for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gave them mans blood mingled with wine to drinke; as <hi>Saluſt</hi> records, <hi>Conjurat. Catilinae.</hi> But theſe miſcreants ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed them; for the confirmation of this their covenant was the receiving of the Euchariſt or Sacrament. Some of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles were theſe, That they would not leave in this Iſland one <hi>Brittiſh</hi> man alive, either <hi>Engliſh, Scotch or Welſh,</hi> no ſo much as any footſteps of them, but would utterly deſtroy all, both Houſes, Cattel, Orchards, Hedg-rowes, &amp;c. <hi>Item,</hi> if any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man ſhould be found who had married an <hi>Iriſh</hi> woman, and had children of her, both he and his children, becauſe they bore his name, ſhould periſh: but if an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man had married an <hi>Engliſh</hi> woman, both ſhe and her children ſhould live.</p>
            <p n="5">5. After all this blood-devouring ferity, they grew more and more outragious daily, and ſcornfully<note n="*" place="margin">See Sr. John Temple <hi>of the Iriſh rebellion.</hi>
               </note> rejected all terms of peace at any time tendred unto them, while they had power to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: and therefore cannot expect any favour when the Lord ſhall deliver them into your hands, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.10, — 13.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Since the righteous God hath evidently manifeſted oft-times from Heaven his great abhorrency of their moſt ſavage cruelties, and hath ſhortned their hornes; that they can do no more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief (as formerly) they ſtill continue <hi>Amalek</hi>-like to cut off ſuch as they meet by the way, ſick, faint, weak and wounded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are caſt behind our Camps.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In ſtead of manifeſting repentance for all their blaſphemies and numberleſſe wicked practiſes, though they have made the land an <hi>Aceldama</hi> from one end thereof to another, and in their skirts have been found the blood of the ſoules of poore innocents, (as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.34.) yet are they ſo far from repenting, that they boaſt much till this day, of what pranks they have committed, and what tortures they inflicted on the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (as they call us:) and repent themſelves of nothing, but for letting any at all eſcape alive from among them, ratifying theſe and ſuch like aſſertions with hideous oathes, becauſe they would have the world to believe them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. What was <hi>Hanuns</hi> villany to theirs? he cut off the garments of two or three men by the middle, and ſo ſent them away; theſe hell-bred monſters ripped up the bowels of men and women and hung them up like ſlaughtered beeves, ſearching their guts for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137660:12"/> gold, compelled children to execute their parents, and parents their children, ſlew husbands, and raviſhed the wives, inticed ſome ignorant and unſtable ſouls to go with them to their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Maſſes, and then forthwith hanged them, while they were (as they ſaid) in a good mind, and thus they endeavoured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both their bodies and ſouls at once.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But they were not all alike: will you condemn all for ſome?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No indeed, The men were <hi>more inhumane than ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages:</hi> the women were <hi>far worſe than the men,</hi> and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <hi>ſurpaſſed them both.</hi> But what have I called them? men and women? they may fitly be compared to that beaſt which <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> c. 13.2. <hi>Like to a Leopard with the feet of a Bear, and the mouth of a lion,</hi> for no one wild beaſt can half expreſſe their malice and cruelty. The Leopard excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all bruit creatures in hatred to man, ſo that in his rage he will tear his very picture in pieces, whereſoever he ſees it, if he can poſſibly come near it: no leſſe have theſe children of <hi>Belial</hi> hated the Image of God in his people, endeavouring to quench the Light of his Goſpel in the blood of the ſincereſt Profeſſors of it; for againſt ſuch have they been moſt furious, and herein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled fell Lions, and have been more ravenous after prey than any wild Bears in the Forreſt: It hath been their holy-day work to hunt Boys and Girls with dogs and ſpaniels like ducks in the water, till they have drowned them; and it hath been their great delight all the week after to diſcourſe of their Sundays diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</p>
            <p>O ye enemies of all righteouſneſſe, ſhall not the Lord viſit for theſe things? ſhall not his ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as you? if <hi>Cain</hi> were ſo accurſed for killing one righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> Gen. 4.11. whoſe blood yet cries againſt him and you; how accurſed ſhall you be for ever, who have murthered in a rage rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching up to heaven, ſo many thouſand ſouls, innocent <hi>quoad vos,</hi> howſoever otherwiſe they were ſinners before the Lord?<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.9, 10.</note> are there not with you ſins, even worſe ſins alſo? If they be deſervedly pronounced accurſed in my Text that ſhould keep their ſword from the blood of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> whoſe iniquities were every way far ſhort of yours; how accurſed muſt you needs be, for whoſe ſake others ſhall be accurſed; if they ſpare you? were you but ſenſible what maſſes of wrath are coming upon you for your but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherings
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137660:12"/> of ſo many both Saints, Prophets, and Infants, as well as others, as one day will appear, before your Judge and theirs; would you but take to heart what terrors and torments ſhall there arreſt you, and for ever abide upon you in the loweſt Hell; it were ſufficient to drive you and all your abettors, (as it hath done ſome of you already) to diſtraction and deſperation.</p>
            <p>True it is, judgment began at the houſe of God, you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held it, yea, and executed it on them: but have the righteous ſcarcely been ſaved, what ſhall be the end of ſuch impious blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, curſed Idolaters, and deſperare infringers of all Laws both humane and divine, both of nature and Religion, as you?</p>
            <p>Repent therefore of all your wickedneſſe, and pray God, if it be poſſible, that you may be forgiven, for you are in the gall of bitterneſſe, and faſt bound in the chains of your iniquities, which have begun already to find you out: and if ye continue to ſtop your ears at the voice of the charmer, (with the deaf adder in the Pſalme) charm he never ſo wiſely, as ever hitherto you have done, ſince I knew you, the wrath of God ſhall fall upon you to the uttermoſt in this world and in the world to come. The worſt I wiſh you is this, that ye may return, that your ſouls may live.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> This may ſerve <hi>for a warning to us and all other people of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to beware of Moabs ſins</hi> mentioned in this Chapter, namely, Confidence in the arme of fleſh, Riches, humane force, Policy, Idols, Contempt of God, and Scorning of true Godlineſſe, Pride and Haughtineſſe; and if we be guilty of any of them, as indeed the inhabitants of theſe Lands are generally moſt hainouſly guilty, let us repent of them with ſpeed; for the bloody reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſword is drawn, and hath begun here in <hi>Ireland</hi> to eat our fleſh and drink our blood, as long before it hath done in the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> and in <hi>Germany,</hi> but we would not take warning by them; and now except <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> take warning by them and us, and prevent it in time, the Lord is about to raiſe up againſt them alſo their worſt enemies, with this charge in the Text injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the ſame penalty of the curſe more dreadful than that in the Poet, <hi>Occupet extremum ſcabies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Horat.</hi> de arte Poetica.</note> Curſed be he that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth his ſword from blood; for queſtionleſſe we and they are guilty of the forementioned ſins of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> and many worſe. Return, Return, why will you die without remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>5</label> Exhortation to all you that are, and all that ſhall be called to this work of the Lord againſt this rebellious Nation, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:137660:13"/> Antichriſtian forces, hereafter to be ſincere and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo</hi> Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in Tacticis. <hi>c. 1. n. 3. 6.</hi> Ante omnes res, maximè belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas conſultores adhibe ad exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; fideles: rem verò de quâ deliberaſti omni studio ac diligentiâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendas ad exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perducere.</note> diligent in executing this divine commiſſion, as you and they would deſire to eſcape his reiterated malediction here denounced againſt all that ſhall be negligent and deceitful in purſuance thereof: How can you ſpare ſuch as the Lord hath deſigned to deſtruction for blood-guiltineſſe, unleſſe you be content that your owne lives go for their lives? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. If you ſpare them, the curſe ſhall not ſpare you; whether it be for favour or affection, or old acquaintance, for kindreds or countreys ſake, or for gain or pleaſure of friends, or any other reſpect, it ſhall avail them but for a ſhort time, and diſadvantage your ſelves for ever: for God ſhall deſtroy you with them either immediatly, or by others, whom he ſhall ſend to accompliſh this <hi>his work</hi> with vigor in your ſteads: and then ſhall you know, <hi>there hath been a Prophet among you.</hi> If any ſhall pretend that pity is to be ſhewed, where God requires juſtice to be executed: or that there is a neceſſity of making a ceſſation with them, when God and the world know the contrary; that perſon whoſoever he be, ſhall bring upon himſelf and upon his poſterity all the innocent blood that they have ſpilt. Now <hi>after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great treſpaſſes, ſeeing that our God hath puniſhed us leſſe than our iniquities deſerve, and hath given us ſuch deliverance as this, ſhould we again break his Commandements, and joyn in league with the people of theſe abominations? would not our God be angry with us, till he had conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping?</hi> Ezra 9.13.14. Deut. 7.2. <hi>Thou ſhalt make no covenant with theſe people, nor ſhew mercy to them.</hi> and <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Make no league with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But thoſe were <hi>Canaanites,</hi> theſe are Chriſtians that you now ſpeak againſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is too good a name to call them <hi>Canaanites,</hi> they may more fitly be termed <hi>Cannibals.</hi> Secondly, unleſſe you be veiled Papiſts, you muſt confeſſe they are as vile Idolaters as ever brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Your allegations are fetched out of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but we live under the new, which is a better Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This makes nothing for them, but much againſt them: for Goſpel vengeance will be the ſoreſt vengeance of all other, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. 2. The New Teſtament condemneth making leagues with Idolaters, as much as the old. Read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:137660:13"/>3. The Goſpel no waies protecteth wilfull murtherers, but calleth for juſtice upon them as the Law requireth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. and <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.10. <hi>They that take the ſword</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>ſhall periſh by the ſword; he that killeth with the ſword</hi> (ſaith his Apoſtle <hi>John) muſt be killed with the ſword:</hi> and yet the worſt is behind; for after this life ended both Murtherers and Idolaters <hi>ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone: which is the ſecond death,</hi> Rev. 21.8. And is not all this new Teſtament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But you are Miniſters of the Goſpel of peace, you ſhould preach peace: bloody preaching and bloody praying ſhould be far from you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Parcius iſta viris.</hi> Shall you plead for rebels and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and condemn us for crying out for juſtice to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge, and his ſubſtitutes?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Do we pray any otherwiſe than the ſoules under the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar even of them that were ſlain for the word of God, did, who cryed with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> Rev. 6.10. And although you condemn theſe our prayers, our Lord Jeſus aſſureth us that his father will hear them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.6. Where he is pleaſed to demand both of you and us, <hi>Shall not God avenge his owne elect, which cry day and night unto him, though he bear long with them? I tell you that he will avenge them ſpeedily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. But the ſeven Nations are expreſly nominated whom God enjoyneth <hi>Iſrael</hi> to deſtroy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.2. You have no ſuch particular rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> You have heard Chriſts expreſſe Command that all that take the ſword ſhall periſh by the ſword: and a particular rule is given how Anti-Chriſt is to be dealt with, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Reward her as ſhe rewarded you, and double unto her double according to her works.</hi> See then what theſe Popiſh conſpirators, Anti-Chriſts limbs, have done to the Proteſtants, being inſtigated thereunto by <hi>Romes</hi> Emiſſaries, Prieſts, Friers, and Jeſuits, you may do the like to them, yea it is juſt to render to them double; for God hath ſo commanded it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But what if they had the Kings Commiſſion for what they did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So they pretended<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phelim O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neale</hi> at his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ'd that they gave out at their firſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, they had the Kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for what they did; but took it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his death it was falſe.</note> for their owne excuſe. But were it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137660:14"/> ſo indeed, Had not <hi>Doeg</hi> I pray you, the Kings command to ſmite <hi>Ahimelech</hi> with the City of the Prieſts? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.18. <hi>The King ſaid to Doeg turn thou and fall upon the Prieſts. And Doeg the Edomite fell on the Prieſts, and ſlew on that day fourſcore and five perſons that did wear a linnen Ephod;</hi> yet becauſe this was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly done, the Kings warrant would not excuſe him: but the Prophet threateneth him in the name of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.5. ſaying, <hi>God ſhall likewiſe deſtroy thee for ever, he ſhall take thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and pluck thee out of thy dwelling place, and root thee out of the land of the living. Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But <hi>Doeg</hi> exceeded his Commiſſion; for he ſmote not the Prieſts alone with the edge of the ſword, but men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alſo, children, and ſucklings, and Oxen, and aſſes, and ſheep; and therefore was he thus puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Did <hi>Doeg</hi> exceed his Commiſſion? therein alſo have theſe <hi>Iriſh Edomites</hi> exceeded him: their little finger hath been heavier than his loins, and therefore muſt expect a farre heavier puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He deſtroyed only the City <hi>Nob,</hi> they left but few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroyed in the whole Land: and their intent was, if their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign had proceeded in ſurprizing this City of <hi>Dublin</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to have left in this land not one man, woman or child of our Religion alive. Remember O Lord theſe children of <hi>Edom,</hi> who cryed in the day of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> raſe it, raſe it even to the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de civit. Dei <hi>l. 1. c. 7.</hi> Quòd innſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ rerumfacie immanitas bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bara mitior ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paruit, ut qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam parceten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, hoc Chriſti nomini tribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Abſit, ☞ Ut prudens quiſ quam hoc feritati imputet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orum.</note>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 7. If they had been ſo ſavage and mercileſſe, as you would render them; they might have deſtroyed many more, when they had them in their hands, who yet ſurvive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord whoſe hook was in their noſtrils to preſerve a remnant alive, as it is this day: but ſure we are, the tender mercies of the wicked were cruel; for when ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtripped in froſt and ſnow, others being wounded alſo thought it impoſſible to travel 40 or 50 miles in that caſe, and ſo choſe death rather than life, theſe <hi>Hamans</hi> uſual anſwer was, no, they would not ſhew them ſo much favour as to kill them, for then they ſhould put them too ſoon out of their pain: whereas on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide; if they perceived any to be fearful of death, and to beg for life, ſuch they cut off incontinently, no intreaties would prevail. Call you this pity, in requitall whereof a Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be granted them upon their firſt demand? My
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137660:14"/> Lords, till meer neceſſity enforced them, they never ſought it: when any advantage ſhall be given them, they will never keep it. Sad experiments of their former perfidiouſneſſe from every quarter can witneſſe this. Say unto them therefore as <hi>Jehu</hi> did to <hi>Jehoram, what have you to do with peace,</hi> ſo long as your wilful murthers and execrable blaſphemies remain? blood defileth the land: and the land cannot be cleanſed of the <hi>blood that is ſhed therein, but by the blood of him that ſhed it,</hi> Numb. 35.33. Now the Lord hath armed you with power, put on <hi>Davids</hi> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and ſay, <hi>we will early deſtroy all the wicked of the land,</hi> Pſa. 101.8. He that ſhould puniſh capital offenders, and doth not, when he may,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Corn.</hi> à La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide in locum.</note> is as guilty before the Lord, as if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had perpetrated all that they have done:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch.</hi> in Lacon. moral. Hoc est ſcele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratos ad malc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicia armare. <hi>Nazianzen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yea more, he ſhall be guilty of all the wickedneſſe that ever afterwards they ſhall commit. I have read how a King of <hi>France</hi> complained that one man had been pardoned twice for murther, and yet he had ſlain a third man: his jeſter ſtanding by ſayd to the King, nay, my Liege, he killed but one, and you ſlew the other two; for if you had cauſed him to have been executed for the firſt fact,<note n="*" place="margin">Si primum non condonaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, reliqua non perpetreſset. erat <hi>Ludovic. XI.</hi> rex Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae.</note> he had never lived to have committed the ſecond and third. So may I ſay to you, ſome of theſe Rebels, and more of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors have rebelled thrice within theſe 47 years ſpace, had they then received condign puniſhments according to their juſt deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, theſe miſchiefs had not now iſſued from them. No marvel then that the curſe denounced againſt all partial indulgent and deceitful workers in this particular be doubled in my text, <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that doth the Lords work negligently,</hi> and again, <hi>Curſed be he that keepeth his ſword from blood;</hi> where the ingemination denoteth four things, 1. <hi>The ſuddenneſſe of the curſe.</hi> 2. <hi>The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.</hi> 3. <hi>The greatneſſe,</hi> and 4. <hi>the continuance of it. q. d.</hi> If you dally and delay in ſo weighty a buſineſſe, God will not dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or delay with you; if you deal doubly with him, he will ſend a double curſe upon you; if you ſleight his work of doing juſtice, heavy judgments ſhall light upon you; either deal truly with him this once, or he will never truſt you more; if you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour his enemies, his fierce and durable plagues ſhall fall upon you and your friends, like fire, and there ſhall be none to quench it. My Lords, the interpretation be to your enemies, and let the Lords Councel be acceptable to you, as you deſire to prevent this curſe, 1. It is threatned againſt the deceitful.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137660:15"/> 2. Againſt the ſlothfull in the Lords work. Bee you then, 1. Faithfull therein. 2. Diligent. This was <hi>Davids Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium, who is ſo faithfull as David?</hi> 1 Sam. 22.14. Though King <hi>Saul</hi> ill requited him for it; yet the Lord the God of truth commendeth him very highly for the Integrity of his heart. <hi>The faithful man ſhall abound with bleſſings,</hi> Pro. 28.20. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Curſed be the deceiver</hi> either 1. In the things of God, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14. or 2. In tranſactions with men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.12. <hi>If I ſeem to my father</hi> (ſaid <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Rebekah) as a deceiver, I ſhall bring a curſe upon me, and not a bleſſing.</hi> Or 3. In martial affairs, here in my Text. Shall any think that the Judge of heaven and earth will tolerate partiality in matters of life and death? will you hold with the hound, and run with the hare? ſhall your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be on this ſide, and your hearts on the other? <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, God is not mocked. Bloody and deceitful men ſhall not live out half their days,</hi> Pſal. 55.23. I will ſet before you but one Preſident: <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> deſerved to be cut off, old <hi>Eli</hi> ſpared them (for they were his ſons) but God neither ſpared him nor them, nor any of his race, becauſe his ſons made themſelves vile and he reſtrained them not: <hi>for this iniquity will I judge his houſe for ever,</hi> ſaith the Lord, and further ſweareth, <hi>it ſhall never be purged with ſacrifice,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.13, 14. Muſt juſtice then be done upon ſons? Judges may not think, that they may put to death whom they will, and whom they will they may keep alive: They may not ſpare a guilty ſon or brother.</p>
            <p>The ſecond word of your Charge is diligence. <hi>Motives</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The work is the Lords.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His eye is upon you from one end of the year to the other; therefore eye-ſervice is not here forbidden, as it is to maſters according to the fleſh, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is the only Maſter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.10. therefore what we do for him, it muſt be done with all our might, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. No ſervice will be accepted of him without diligence, for it cannot be ſeparated from his love, as the notation of the word in latine imports: and ſo much is intimated by the embleme of the firſtling of an aſſe, which was not to be offered up in ſacrifice, but to be redeemed with a lamb, or elſe the neck of it was to be broken, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.20. ſhewing that God abhorreth ſloth and ſluggiſhneſſe in all undertakings for him.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note>5. He giveth the beſt wages, if men be diligent.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:137660:15"/>6. He puniſheth the ſlothful here and everlaſtingly.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.26.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Our enemies are vigilant, their feet are ſwift to ſhed blood, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.7.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Our delays and negligence giveth them great advantage. By this onely ſtratagem procraſtination <hi>Q. Fabius Max.</hi> recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the loſt eſtate of the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo averreth <hi>Ennius, Unus homo nobis cunctando reſtituit rem.</hi> Expedition as our caſe now ſtands will doe us as much good.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As the treacherous perſon is accurſed, ſo is<note n="*" place="margin">Sophoc. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, being here included under the ſame word, and involved in the ſame twofold curſe, to wit, 1. In the life to come; and 2. In this world. 1. He ſhall be accurſed in ſoul, and 2. Body, 3. In his undertakings, and 4. Poſterity. This may make the ears of all ſuch to tingle, as ſend relief to beſieged places, but not till they have intimation they are taken: and of ſuch as inſinuate themſelves into our counſels, I had almoſt ſaid Councils purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inform the enemy, of ſuch alſo that come to take up arms among us, that they may fly to the enemy when they meet with the firſt opportunity, and ſo uſe them againſt us: or that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſert their fellows, when they have moſt need, that they may be ſurprized by ſuch as they more affect, or that in ſtead of ſhooting at the Rebels, ſhoot into the aire, or into their fellows or Commanders bodies. Shall not God find out theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceitful workers? yes, and the curſe too. He that is more true than they can be falſe, hath fore-ſpoken it, and he will make it good, when he begins, he will make an end, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>Here by the way, before I proceed to the laſt Uſe, let me hint unto my brethren of the Miniſtry a note of<note n="*" place="margin">Si juſſu Dei ſermo Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus hic ſubji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit eos maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioni qui neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentèr occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, quantas nos poenas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olvemus, ſi mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſpirituale parvi pepende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus? <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Theodorets</hi> upon my Text to this effect, If Souldiers <hi>fall under</hi> a double curſe through their negligence in ſparing the temporal lives of them, whom God hath adjudged to the ſword; how many and great curſes ſhall fall upon ſuch Miniſters as through negligence deſtroy the ſouls of them whom God hath ſent them to ſave, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>Conſolation.</hi> And ſo I paſſe from mount <hi>Eball</hi> to mount <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizzim</hi> to pronounce bleſſings in the name of the Lord upon all thoſe that are,<note place="margin">Deut. 27.12.13.</note> or ſhall be active and faithful in this work of the Lord, according to the directions of his word formerly laid down. This war is juſt, be well aſſured that it is your duty to proſecute the ſame, and then before you go forth to battel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb facs="tcp:137660:16"/> you of all your ſins ſince you are now called to puniſh others for theirs, begin with prayer to him who giveth victory to whom he pleaſeth; proceed in faith, confidently relying upon his mercy and faithfull promiſes; Caſt off all fear of men, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilanimity of ſpirit. Be of good courage, and fight valiantly for the cauſe of God and his people againſt theſe Anti-Chriſtian ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and leave the ſucceſſe to God. Be obedient to the lawfull commands of your ſuperiours: and be juſt among your ſelves, and towards all men, wrong no innocent perſon in the leaſt matter. Let the ends which you propound to your ſelves be the glory of God, the puniſhment of enormous offenders, the preſervation of good men in their lives and eſtates, and the happy reſtauration of peace in the Church and Common-wealth. And as many as walk according to theſe Rules <hi>peace be upon them and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi> They ſhall be bleſſed in <hi>this life</hi> in their ſouls, bodies undertakings, and poſterities, and <hi>in the life to come.</hi> Chriſtian, Souldiers, we ſeek not to bring you into a fools paradiſe, as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So Pope</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas <hi>the firſt in his reſcripts. l.</hi> concilior. <hi>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3.</hi> Quiſquis in hoc belli certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine fideliter mortuus fuerit, illi regna coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestia minime negabuntur.</note> ſome Popes have uſed to do their Proſelites, by promiſing them heaven who ſhould wage their wars ſtrenuouſly; as if heaven were at their diſpoſing: but the Lord himſelf who hath all power in heaven and earth, whoſe ſervants you are, ſhall bleſſe you. He hath curſed your enemies already (as you have heard) and as they have begun to fall, they ſhall fall before you, but you ſhall remain bleſſings even to others of your own Nation and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea all the congregations of the Saints ſhall bleſſe you, and God for you. As <hi>Melchizedek</hi> Prieſt of the moſt high God met <hi>Abram</hi> when he returned from that famous ſervice, the ſlaughter of the five Kings, who had before taken his Nephew <hi>Lot</hi> priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſpoiled all the countries round about, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14, 19, 20. and <hi>bleſſed him,</hi> ſaying, <hi>bleſſed be Abram of the moſt high God, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of heaven and earth: and bleſſed be the moſt high God, which hath delivered thine enemies into thine hand.</hi> Thus <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak</hi> having brought in the Angel of the Lord charging all the world to curſe <hi>Meroz,</hi> yea and again to curſe bitterly the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof; becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty. And juſtly they deſerved this curſe, this double curſe; for if they be accurſed in my Text, that do the Lords work, when they perform it negligently; how much more curſed ſhall they be who will do nothing at all for God, or for his cauſe and people? Then they <hi>pronounce</hi> bleſſings upon <hi>Jael the
<pb facs="tcp:137660:16"/> wife of Heber the Kenite</hi> for her manful executing of <hi>Siſera,</hi> Judg. 5.23, 24. Saying, <hi>Bleſſed ſhall ſhe be above women,</hi> and again, <hi>Bleſſed ſhall ſhe be above women in the tent;</hi> where the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> is doubled as was the <hi>Curſe</hi> before. And hence obſerve with me in the laſt place, that we read of two women in Scripture who are pronounced bleſſed above women, the <hi>one is in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of our Lord, <hi>for bringing forth a Saviour into the world: the other in the Old Teſtament,</hi> namely this <hi>Jael for ſmiting dead that curſed enemy</hi> of Gods Church <hi>Siſera.</hi> And this brings me <hi>vice Coronidis</hi> to ſpeak ſomthing of this decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and bleſſed Knight, whoſe Obſequies we are met to ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize at this time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Teſtimony given to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> CHARLES COOTE, who died Honourably in the Churches &amp; his Countries ſervice, and with exceeding great Lamentation was Interred in Chriſt-Church <hi>Dublin,</hi> the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>May,</hi> 1642.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthy and Chriſtian Auditors,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe time being far ſpent, I ſhall utter but little of that which might be ſpoken of this renowned and bleſſed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Glory, and his Nations good, who was well known to us all to be faithful till death in the Lords work, and in his life a true mirrour of Piety, Proweſſe, and Prudence, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Induſtry both in times of peace and of war.</p>
               <p>Before theſe commotions in <hi>Ireland</hi> began, it pleaſed the Lord to viſit him with ſickneſſe, and to convince him of his ſins: after his recovery he ſent for ſome ſpiritual Phyſitians to whom ingenuouſly he opened the eſtate of his ſoul, and took their counſel what he might do to procure pardon and reconciliation with God, heedfully obſerving what was ſayd, and carefully making uſe of it afterwards (I doubt not) to his everlaſting good. For ever ſince he hath been obſerved to
<pb facs="tcp:137660:17"/> be a very due reſorter to publick ordinances, and a large contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter towards their maintenance, having in high eſteem the faithful meſſengers of Jeſus Chriſt, and expreſſing ſingular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the generation of Gods people. He was like <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion frequent in prayer, abundant in alms-deeds. His proweſſe rendred him terrible to our enemies round about, and the Lord of Hoſts made him ſucceſſefull; for as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Jonathan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>From the blood of the ſlain, and from the fat of the mighty his ſword returned not empty.</hi> His rare dexterity in animating the Souldier, his winning demeanour, affable and ſeaſonable ſpeeches, and his prudent ordering of his affairs, <hi>made him great among his people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 10.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and accepted</hi> (with <hi>Mordecai) of the multitude of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> for they all ſaw he ſought the welfare of his Nation, and put his life in his hand to procure their ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fines Moriſon</note>He was a man of war from his youth. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Chronicle relateth he came hither a Captain in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> wars, <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. <hi>Sept.</hi> 4. And did memorable exploits againſt <hi>Tirone</hi> and his complices. As the Lord made him inſtrumental to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce peace, ſo he was vigilant to preſerve it afterwards. Many combinations of theeviſh Crews, and trayterous conſpiracies in the Province of <hi>Connaght</hi> and Confines of <hi>Ulſter</hi> hath he diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, making ſome moſt notorious offenders exemplary to the terror of the reſt.<note place="margin">Job 29, 12.13, 14.</note> On the other ſide, delivering the poor innocent from ſuch as were too ſtrong for them. <hi>He brake the jaws of the wicked, and plucked the ſpoil out of their teeth. The bleſſing of them that were ready to periſh came upon him: and he cauſed the ſtrangers heart to ſing for joy. He put on righteouſneſſe and it clothed him, and his judgment was as a robe and diadem.</hi> Many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether did he ſhine as an eminent Star in our Horizon: nothing danted with falſe aſperſions of ſome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Maximus</hi> Serm. <hi>54.</hi> In ſole ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riò umbra ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate viventes invidia comita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> or fooliſh credulity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for he knew that as the ſhadow follows the body walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Sun, ſo doth envy attend worth and vertue.</p>
               <p>Since this new eruption of war, he only was left of all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient worthies in the former wars of <hi>Ireland</hi> whom time either hath worn out, or diſabled for this work, but the Lord renewed his ſtrength as the Eagles; when hearing the rufull out-cries, and beholding the prodigious miſeries of our ſtript <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which ſurpaſſe all expreſſion, he was exceedingly moved in his ſpirit, and prayed the Lord to endue him with ſtrength from above, that he might be able before he died to give three or four defeats to
<pb facs="tcp:137660:17"/> the authours of the great indignities and numberleſſe ſufferings of an helpleſſe people. This prayer the Lord condeſcended to; for inſtantly, of weak he became ſtrong, and to all mens admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on went forth in confidence of aſſiſtance of the moſt high, and by Faith put to flight thoſe that roſe up againſt him; and who ſaw not, that God was with him? Firſt he diſcomfited the Rebels in <hi>Wicklow:</hi> he burned <hi>Clantarf,</hi> a place neer this City filled with rapine and blood: he took in the Garriſons of the <hi>Naaz,</hi> and <hi>Trim:</hi> he expeld the enemies out of the <hi>Navan,</hi> and then he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with the whole body of the enemy at <hi>Kilruſh</hi> in a pitcht battel, and routed their vaſt multitudes, and would have purſued them, if he might have had his will, with ſuch heat and vigor, that they ſhould have had little leaſure or opportunity to rally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more: but he was called back, and the number of his deſired victories being made up with ſome overplus, in his laſt battel near <hi>Trim</hi> he was ſlain, being ſhot (as it is verily conjectured) by one of our ſide, into the body; having a little before with three or four Troops, chaſed three or four thouſand almoſt two miles, and left about four hundred dead on the place; Thus died this honorable Patriot and Champion in the Lords work, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, in the ſixty fifth year of his age,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic.</hi> de Senect.</note> wherein (as <hi>Cato</hi> Major ſaith of <hi>Q. Maximus, Hic bella gerebat, ut adoleſcens, cum plane grandis eſſet.</hi>) he was like <hi>Caleb</hi> for ſtrength,<note place="margin">Joſ. 14.11.</note> as able for the war both to go out and to come in as he was the day when he was firſt ſent over, having about a quarter of an hour before his fall, ſlain with his ſword a Rebel of great ſtature hand to hand. But now as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Abner,</hi> may I ſay of him, <hi>A great man is fallen in our Iſrael;</hi> in whom the Lord hath bereaved us at once of the mighty man, and the man of war, the prudent and valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the honorable man, and the Counſellour;<note place="margin">c. 3.2.</note> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>The greatneſſe of our adverſaries rejoycings at his fall, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth aloud the greatneſſe of our loſſe: but nothing hath befallen him or us, but what hath befallen the deareſt of Gods Servants. <hi>Sampſon</hi> is reckoned in the Catalogue of Believers,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> who ſlew more ar his death than in all his life; yet he periſhed among the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines:</hi> by the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> ſword gracious <hi>Jonathan</hi> afterwards fell upon Mount <hi>Gilboa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.20.</note> which occaſioned much triumph to the daughters of the uncircumciſed. Faithfull <hi>Uriah</hi> was alſo betrayed by <hi>Joab</hi> at the Kings Command, and cut off by the ſword of the
<pb facs="tcp:137660:18"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:137660:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> children of <hi>Ammon;</hi> Adde to theſe, godly <hi>Joſiah,</hi> to whom there was none like before or after among all the Kings of <hi>Judah;</hi> yet was he ſlain by the ſword of <hi>Pharaoh Necho.</hi> The ſword de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth one as well as another: and all things befall all alike, him that feareth God, and him that feareth him not. Yea <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth this kind of death the moſt beautifull of all other. <hi>Ethic.</hi> l. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Offic. l. 1.</hi> &amp; de ſomnio Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionis.</note> c. 6. The Orator affirmeth, that no good man will doubt to die for the profit of his Country: This our deceaſed Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion accounted to be moſt eligible; for ſuch as lay down their lives for the brethren eminently ſhew forth their love to God and his Church,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.16.</note> as Gods love is apparently ſeen in his ſons lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his life for us. And wiſe men in all ages agree upon this maxime, <hi>Decet Imperatorem ſtantem mori:</hi> And God gave him his option, he was taken from us by this eligible, beautifull, honourable death; for he deceaſed on Horſ-back, being upheld by his Son riding behind him, till he had brought him to his quarters. The Lord convince and humble us all for all our ſins, which have brought this judgment upon us. Not one but many <hi>Achans</hi> have thus troubled our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for I know no kind of ſins which are not predominant among us. It is the Lords mercy we are not all conſumed.</p>
               <p>The Lord help us to look up to Jeſus Chriſt, whom our ſins have alſo pierced,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.4.</note> for him hath God given to be a leader and commander to his people; who once died, that by his death we may have life, and by his life ſalvation temporal and eternal; for now, though other Commanders die, he liveth for ever, and when other helpers may be far off, he is ever preſent with all his people who alone can help, when as without him all help of men is in vain; as when the Spirit departed ttom valiant <hi>Sampſon,</hi> he became weak like other men. This hath he commanded us to do, and promiſed ſalvation to all them that ſo do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. And then ſhall our ſorrows be all turned into joy, and our enemies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing ſhall vaniſh: then ſhall the Lord who hath the reſidue of the ſpirit in the room of this one Heroick Patriot now gone to his reſt, raiſe up many deliverers endued with wiſdome, counſell, and might, and the fear of the Lord, who may fight our Battels, tread down our enemies as mire in the Streets, reſtore poor out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts to their rightfull poſſeſſions again, and ſettle peace and truth in all the borders of this ſinfull and bloody Land, to the comfort of all true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and his own everlaſting glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
